Guide to the Gillette family papers, 1876-1922.
Gillette family papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Gillette Family Papers, 1876-1922
4456
Gillette family
1.1 cubic ft.; 1 portrait.
Letters, scrapbooks, and 1 painting.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Letters and scrapbooks documenting the lives of Edwin S. and Flora Spence Gillette.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Edwin S. Gillette graduated from Cornell University in 1873. He married Flora Spence; their sons were Douglas Graves Gillette (1890-1964), Class of 1912; Edwin "Red" Spence Gillette (1891-1961), Class of 1914; and Paul Gillette (1896-1980), Class of 1918.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Travel scrapbooks kept by Edwin S. Gillette from Cuba, 1905, Jamaica, 1906, and Europe and Egypt, 1922; and a scrapbook kept by Flora Spence Gillette commemorating her trips around the United States and abroad with dried flowers, leaves, and other vegetation. World War I letters and memorabilia from Paul Gillette when he served with the Medical Department of the Quartermaster Corps, American Expeditionary Force, to his family, 1917-1918, including letters from the U.S. Army Medical Officers Training Camp, Ft. Oglethorpe, Ga., the Young Men's Christian Association of the United States National War Work Council, the YMCA of the City of New York Army Branch, and Evacuation Hospital #6. Also, portrait of Edwin S. Gillette by Professor I. P. Church.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Gillette family.; Gillette, Edwin S., d. 1926.; Gillette, Flora Spence.; Gillette, Douglas Graves, 1890-1964.; Gillette, Edwin Spence, 1891-1961.; Gillette, Paul, 1896-1980.; United States. Army Medical Dept.; YMCA of the USA. National War Work Council.; Young Men's Christian Association (New York, N.Y.); United States. Army. Evacuation Hospital, 6th.
Subjects:
World War, 1914-1918--Participation, American.
Places:
Cuba--Description and travel.; Jamaica--Description and travel.; Europe--Description and travel.; Egypt--Description and travel.; Medical Officers' Training Camp (Ga.)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Letters
Box 1
Series II. Scrapbooks
Boxes 1 and 2
Series III. Portrait
Map Case V
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Letters
  - Letters from Paul Gillette (C.U.'18) to his father, Edwin S. Gillette (C.U. 1873), Jan. 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Paul Gillette to Edwin S. Gillette, Aug. 1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters from Paul Gillette to Edwin S. Gillette, Sept. 1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters from Paul Gillette to Edwin S. Gillette, Oct. 1917 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters from Paul Gillette to Edwin S. Gillette, Nov. 1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters from Paul Gillette to Edwin S. Gillette, Dec. 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters from Paul Gillette to Edwin S. Gillette, Jan. 1917 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters from Paul Gillette, Feb. 1918; To Edwin S. ("Red", C.U.'14), Douglas Graves Gillette, (C.U.'12), and Maude Gillette. (Edwin S. "Red" and Douglas are Paul's brothers; Maude is the wife of Douglas.) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters from Paul Gillette to Edwin S. Gillette, Feb. 1918 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters from Paul Gillette to Edwin S. Gillette, March-April, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters from Paul Gillette to Edwin S. Gillette, April, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters from Paul Gillette to Edwin S. Gillette, May-June, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters from Paul Gillette to Edwin S. Gillette, July-August, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II. Scrapbooks
  - Flora Spence Gillette's scrapbook, July, 1876-1887; Flowers, leaves and other types of vegetation collected from her travels. (Flora was the wife of Edwin S. and the mother of Paul, Douglas and "Red.") (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook, 1922; Consisting mainly of postcards, clippings, and other memorabilia of Edwin S. Gillette's Mediterranean and European tour. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook, Feb. 1906; Kept by Edwin S. Gillette re his trip to Jamaica. He traveled on the United Steamship Company's steamship "Admiral Schley" with William Hazlitt Smith and A.J. Brown of Ithaca, and also many others from around the U.S. The scrapbook consists mainly of photographs, postcards, and magazine clippings. Of particular interest are magazine photographs of George Rodney (Lord Rodney) commander-in-chief at Jamaica from 1771-74; basket, sugar, rum and banana laborers; the hurricane disaster of 1903 and the earthquake of 1907, and various other island scenes. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbook, July, 1905; Kept by Edwin S. Gillette containing postcards, newspaper clippings, photographs and an eight page typed travel journal re his trip to Cuba. Most of the photographs were taken by William Hazlitt Smith dealing with scenes around Havana and Santiago, Cuba. Included in the photos are views of the Cabana fortress, wreck of the battleship Maine, and monuments in honor of Jose Marti, the Cuban patriot, 1853-1895. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Scrapbook, 1917-1919; Postcards, clippings, telegrams, one page of photographs. The letters contained in this scrapbook are from Sergeant Paul Gillette to his father, Edwin S., and his brothers, Edwin S. ("Red") and Douglas and to Art Dean (Arthur Hobson Dean, (C.U.'19.) Several letters and telegrams were sent from Fort Slocum, N.Y., Camp Greenleaf of Fort Oglethorpe, Georgia, but the majority were sent from France before November 18, 1918, probably at Souilly, Meuse, while Gillette was with the Quartermaster Corps, Medical Department, American Expeditionary Force, Evacuation Hospital No.#6. The rest of the letters were sent from Coblenz (on the Rhine River) Germany, while Gillette was with the Quartermaster Corps., Army of the Occupation, Third Army, Evacuation Hospital #27. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series III. Portrait
  - Portrait of Edwin S. Gillette, aged 73, by Professor I.P. Church. (Size 23" by 27".)